{
  "lessonId": "lesson9",
  "lessonTitle": "Урок 9",
  "lessonDescription": "Сьогодні ви взнаєте, як вживати He/She/It у заперечній формі",
  "lessonURL": "DCTjnUlK43o",
  "lessonItems": [
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "He/She/It + <b>does not</b> + verb",
      "startTime": "1:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "does not скорочується до <b>doesn't</b> [daznt]",
      "startTime": "1:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він не говорить англійською вільно",
      "answer":   "He doesn't speak English fluently",
      "startTime": "1:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не розуміє",
      "answer":   "She doesn't understand",
      "startTime": "1:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>foreigner</b> /ˈfɒɹ.ɪ.nə(ɹ)/ іноземець, чужинець",
      "startTime": "2:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не розуміє іноземців",
      "answer":   "She doesn't understand foreigners",
      "startTime": "2:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно не п'є",
      "answer":   "It doesn't drink",
      "startTime": "2:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно не п'є молока",
      "answer":   "It doesn't drink milk",
      "startTime": "2:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>cold</b> /koʊld/ холодний",
      "startTime": "2:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Піт (Pete) не любить холодні вечори",
      "answer":   "Pete doesn't like cold evenings",
      "startTime": "2:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ліз (Liz) не віддає перевагу довгим зборам",
      "answer":   "Liz doesn't prefer long meetings",
      "startTime": "3:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) менеджер не телефонує дуже часто",
      "answer":   [
        "The manager doesn't call very often",
        "The manager doesn't phone very often"
      ],
      "startTime": "3:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Кіт не літає",
      "answer":   "A cat doesn't fly",
      "startTime": "3:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Людина не вірить у погане майбутнє",
      "answer":   "A man doesn't believe in a bad future",
      "startTime": "4:18"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>policeman</b> /pəˈliːsmən/ поліцейський",
      "startTime": "4:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) поліцейський не зупиняє тебе",
      "answer":   "The policeman doesn't stop you",
      "startTime": "4:34"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>bed</b> /bɛːd/ ліжко",
      "startTime": "5:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) робітник не ремонтує (fix) те ліжко",
      "answer":   [
        "The worker doesn't fix that bed",
        "The worker doesn't repair that bed"
      ],
      "startTime": "5:07"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>repair</b> /ɹɪˈpɛə/ ремонтувати",
      "startTime": "5:24"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Зазвичай він не ходить по магазинам ввечері",
      "answer":   "He usually doesn't go shopping in the evening",
      "startTime": "5:42"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не відвідує мене взимку",
      "answer":   "She doesn't visit me in winter",
      "startTime": "5:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вчитель не навчає весь (цей) рік",
      "answer":   "A teacher doesn't teach all the year",
      "startTime": "6:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>umbrella</b> /ʌmˈbɹɛlə/ парасолька",
      "startTime": "6:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Моя сестра не має парасольки",
      "answer":   "My sister doesn't have an umbrella",
      "startTime": "6:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>doesn't have</b> під час заперечень з he/she/it <u>has міняється на have</u><br /><b>DOES не стоїть разом з HAS</b>",
      "startTime": "7:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він не летить до США",
      "answer":   "He doesn't fly to the USA",
      "startTime": "7:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>sell</b> /sɛl/ продавати<br /><b>seller</b> /ˈsɛlə/ продавець<br /><b>cigarette</b> /sɪ.ɡəˈɹɛt/ цигарка",
      "startTime": "8:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Продавець не продає сигарет",
      "answer":   "A seller doesn't sell cigarettes",
      "startTime": "8:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Ця) дівчина не сидить",
      "answer":   "The girl doesn't sit",
      "startTime": "8:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>cake</b> /kʰeɪk/ тістечко<br /><b>bake</b> /beɪk/ пекти",
      "startTime": "9:26"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Моя мама не випікає тістечок",
      "answer":   [
        "My mum doesn't bake cakes",
        "My mother doesn't bake cakes",
        "My mom doesn't bake cakes"
      ],
      "startTime": "9:32"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) кузен не грає у волейбол",
      "answer":   "The cousin doesn't play volleyball",
      "startTime": "9:52"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>eat</b> /iːt/ істи<br /><b>soup</b> /suːp/ суп",
      "startTime": "10:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Його собака не їсть суп",
      "answer":   "His dog doesn't eat soup",
      "startTime": "10:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>soap</b> /soʊp/ мило",
      "startTime": "10:31"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>jump</b> /dʒʌmp/ стрибати, стрибок",
      "startTime": "10:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Той м'яч не підстрибує",
      "answer":   "That ball doesn't jump",
      "startTime": "10:37"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>thrill</b> /θɹɪl/ тремтіти, збуджуватися, хвилюватися<br/><b>thriller</b> /θrɪlɜ/ трилер",
      "startTime": "10:53"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Її дідусь не любить трилерів",
      "answer":   [
        "Her granddad doesn't like thrillers",
        "Her grandfather doesn't like thrillers"
      ],
      "startTime": "10:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>alcohol</b> /ˈæl.kə.hɔl/, /ˈæl.kə.hɑl/ алкоголь",
      "startTime": "11:07"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона зазвичай не п'є алкоголь",
      "answer":   "She usually doesn't drink alcohol",
      "startTime": "11:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>night</b> /naɪt/ ніч",
      "startTime": "11:21"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Пем (Pam) не навчається вночі",
      "answer":   "Pam doesn't study at night",
      "startTime": "11:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>doctor</b> /ˈdɒktə/ лікар, доктор<br/><b>physician</b> /fɪˈzɪʃən/ лікар, медик",
      "startTime": "11:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Цей лікар не працює на (цих) вихідних",
      "answer":   "This doctor doesn't work at the weekend",
      "startTime": "11:45"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це не працює",
      "answer":   "It doesn't work",
      "startTime": "11:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>countryside</b> /ˈkʌn.tɹiˌsaɪd/ сільська місцевість",
      "startTime": "12:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Його сім'я не живе у (цій) сільській місцевості",
      "answer":   "His family doesn't live in the countryside",
      "startTime": "12:16"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони сміються весело",
      "answer":   "They laugh merrily",
      "startTime": "14:54"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти часто відвідуєш її?",
      "answer":   "Do you often visit her?",
      "startTime": "15:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>once</b> /wʌns/, /wʌn(t)s/ раз, один раз<br />><b>away</b> /əˈweɪ/ геть<br/><b>far away</b> /fɑɹ/ далеко",
      "startTime": "15:33"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ні, раз на рік. Кейт (Kate) живе далеко",
      "answer":   "No, once a year. Kate lives far away",
      "startTime": "15:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>dance</b> /dæns/ танець, танцювати<br /><b>together</b> /tʊˈɡɛð.ə(ɹ)/, /təˈɡɛð.ə(ɹ)/ разом",
      "startTime": "16:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Сем (Sam) та Тіна (Tina) танцюють разом?",
      "answer":   "Do Sam and Tina dance together?",
      "startTime": "16:17"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>fly</b> /flaɪ/ літати, муха",
      "startTime": "16:30"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони летять до Чикаго (Chicago)",
      "answer":   "They fly to Chicago",
      "startTime": "16:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>everything</b> /ˈɛvɹɪθɪŋ/ усе, все",
      "startTime": "17:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ви знаєте все",
      "answer":   "You know everything",
      "startTime": "17:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>your</b> /jɔː/, /jʊə/ ваш, твій<br/><b>better</b> /ˈbɛtə/ краще, кращий<br /><b>get better</b> ставати кращим",
      "startTime": "17:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ваша англійська стає кращою",
      "answer":   "Your English gets better",
      "startTime": "17:14"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>school</b> /skuːl/ школа<br/><b>university</b> /juːnɪˈvɜːsətiː/ університет",
      "startTime": "17:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони не навчаються в школі. Вони навчаються в університеті",
      "answer":   "They don't study at school. They study at a university",
      "startTime": "17:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>hot</b> /hɒt/ гарячий<br /><b>chocolate</b> /ˈt͡ʃɔk(ə)lɪt/ шоколад",
      "startTime": "17:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти хочеш гарячий шоколад?",
      "answer":   "Do you want hot chocolate?",
      "startTime": "17:59"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не уявляє цього",
      "answer":   [
        "She doesn't imagine this",
        "She doesn't imagine it"
      ],
      "startTime": "18:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>choir</b> /kwaɪə(ɹ)/ хор",
      "startTime": "19:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він не співає у хорі",
      "answer":   "He doesn't sing in a choir",
      "startTime": "19:10"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>practise</b> /ˈpɹæktɪs/ практикувати",
      "startTime": "19:40"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти практикуєш англійську щодня?",
      "answer":   [
        "Do you practice English every day?",
        "Do you practise English every day?"
      ],
      "startTime": "19:42"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>practice</b> /ˈpɹæktɪs/ практика",
      "startTime": "20:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Ця) дівчина зазвичай не практикує це. Чому?",
      "answer":   [
        "The girl usually doesn't practice it. Why?",
        "The girl usually doesn't practise this. Why?"
      ],
      "startTime": "20:25"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>performance</b> /pəɹ.ˈfɔɹ.məns/ вистава, виконання",
      "startTime": "20:49"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми показуємо (цю) виставу у суботу",
      "answer":   "We show the performance on Saturday",
      "startTime": "20:50"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони покинули Канаду? Я не знаю",
      "answer":   "Do they leave Canada? I don't know",
      "startTime": "21:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти чуєш це?",
      "answer":   "Do you hear it?",
      "startTime": "21:24"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Мій брат не прокидається рано",
      "answer":   [
        "My brother doesn't get up early",
        "My brother doesn't wake up early"
      ],
      "startTime": "21:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>wake up</b> /ˈweɪk/ прокидатися",
      "startTime": "21:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Сьогодні не йде дощ",
      "answer":   "It doesn't rain today",
      "startTime": "21:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>comedy</b> /ˈkɑmədi/ комедія",
      "startTime": "22:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти любиш дивитися комедії?",
      "answer":   "Do you like watching comedies?",
      "startTime": "22:07"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>mean</b> /miːn/ означати, значити",
      "startTime": "22:16"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це означає",
      "answer":   "It means",
      "startTime": "22:17"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Це не означає",
      "answer":   "It doesn't mean",
      "startTime": "23:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти надаєш перевагу молокові чи гарячому шоколаду?",
      "answer":   "Do you prefer milk or hot chocolate?",
      "startTime": "24:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він не спить багато",
      "answer":   "He doesn't sleep a lot",
      "startTime": "24:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>please</b> /pliːz/ будь ласка<br/><b>info</b> /ˈɪnfəʊ/ інформація (неформ.)",
      "startTime": "24:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Будь ласка, поділись цією інформацією",
      "answer":   [
        "Please share this info",
        "Please share this information"
      ],
      "startTime": "24:24"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Мій тато не зустрічає мене сьогодні",
      "answer":   [
        "My dad doesn't meet me today",
        "My father doesn't meet me today"
      ],
      "startTime": "24:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>something</b> /ˈsʌmθɪŋ/ щось, що-небудь, чого-небудь<br/><b>interesting</b> /ˈɪntəɹəstɪŋ/ цікаве",
      "startTime": "24:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він інколи створює щось цікаве",
      "answer":   "He sometimes creates something interesting",
      "startTime": "25:00"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>document</b> /ˈdɑkjʊmɛnt/ документ",
      "startTime": "25:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Поліцейський зазвичай чекає на ваші документи",
      "answer":   "A policeman usually waits for your documents",
      "startTime": "25:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти чуєш мене?",
      "answer":   "Do you hear me?",
      "startTime": "25:34"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми не обговорюємо цього?",
      "answer":   "We don't discuss it",
      "startTime": "25:45"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти робиш замовлення сьогодні?",
      "answer":   "Do you make booking today?",
      "startTime": "25:56"
    }
  ]
}
